<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>LambdaClass Blog - Clojure</title>
      <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com</link>
      <description>Deep technical insights on cryptography, distributed systems, zero-knowledge proofs, and cutting-edge software engineering from the LambdaClass team.</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/tags/clojure/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Simulations are about to get way, way faster with JuliaSim</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/simulations-are-about-to-get-way-way-faster-with-juliasim/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/simulations-are-about-to-get-way-way-faster-with-juliasim/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/simulations-are-about-to-get-way-way-faster-with-juliasim/">&lt;p&gt;Today we’re excited to bring you a first glance at the result of a major multi-year project by the Julia Computing team.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JuliaSim is a cloud-based simulation platform built on top of the Julia open source stack, including SciML and ModelingToolkit, which we explored in depth &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;scientific-machine-learning-with-julia-the-sciml-ecosystem&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;modeling-complexity-with-symbolics-jl-and-modelingtoolkit-jl&#x2F;&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, respectively. These were just the base of JuliaSim, which aims to change the way the industry does modeling and simulation with powerful acceleration and integration within a complete ecosystem.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;juliacomputing.com&#x2F;products&#x2F;juliasim&#x2F;&quot;&gt;JuliaSim&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;’s first beta will be released in a few months. We interviewed Chris Rackauckas to learn more about the project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-juliasim-how-does-it-compare-to-alternatives-like-modelica-dymola&quot;&gt;What is JuliaSim? How does it compare to alternatives like Modelica&#x2F;Dymola?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JuliaSim is a cloud-based platform for accelerated modeling and simulation. Unlike tools like Dymola, it integrates with a large open source community, the Julia programming language and the SciML ecosystem, to enhance its environment with offerings like easy parallelism, automated generation of ML surrogate models, and much more. In &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=lNbU5jNp67s&quot;&gt;a recent talk at JuliaCon 2021&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I highlight this community integration as one of its core aspects that gives JuliaSim a competitive advantage in terms of features and performance, since it allows us to contribute to and benefit from the work of many scientists and engineers from across the world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While JuliaSim has acausal modeling as one of its core features, unlike Modelica-based tools that is just one of its domains. Accelerated simulation of PDEs with neural networks, integrating stochastic simulation into workflows, specific simulation environments for pharmacology and circuit modeling, and much more are all part of the JuliaSim product. We see the future as a place where composability will be necessary to achieve the next level of simulations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;can-it-integrate-with-the-fmi-will-we-be-able-to-use-models-written-in-e-g-modelica-inside-juliasim&quot;&gt;Can it integrate with the FMI? Will we be able to use models written in, e.g. Modelica, inside JuliaSim?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, JuliaSim at its release will offer features for integrating with the FMI standard, allowing for FMI imports and FMI exports. This will allow for example the ability to build surrogates of models from Modelica or Simulink platforms, and allow for generating binaries that can integrate back into these platforms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-key-aspect-of-modelica-is-its-standard-library-which-includes-many-of-the-most-common-components-for-modeling-will-there-be-a-similar-thing-in-juliasim&quot;&gt;A key aspect of Modelica is its standard library, which includes many of the most common components for modeling. Will there be a similar thing in JuliaSim?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With JuliaSim we are building a standard library which includes similar domains to the Modelica Standard Library, but also includes many other domains related to the customers we have been working with. For example, with JuliaSim one will be able to easily search a database of hundreds of physiological and systems biological models for accelerating workflows in biomedical simulation and drug development. We plan to continually improve this model library and mold it to the needs of our customers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-surrogate-models-what-makes-them-important-especially-beyond-academic-applications&quot;&gt;What are surrogate models? What makes them important, especially beyond academic applications?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surrogate models are an amortization of compute cost to improve simulation workflows. It gives you a way to say “do 100 simulations now, and all of my future simulations are 100x faster”. When you mix this with cloud resources you can get a major workflow update: pay for a bit of cloud compute to spawn a bunch of simulations in parallel, but now every time you click the simulate button you do not have to wait 30 minutes to check the result.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was in graduate school I noticed that there is a very nonlinear effect of code speed on productivity which I captured in a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.stochasticlifestyle.com&#x2F;the-nonlinear-effect-of-code-speed-on-productivity&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. If you have to wait 30 minutes for a result, that means that instead you’ll start it before lunch or before a 1 hour meeting, so the true “time to see simulation results” gets amplified further. 2 hour simulations are something you will start in the morning and check at night. Thus a surrogate changing a long simulation to something that you can analyze in real-time is invaluable to decreasing labor costs because of how simulation time effects the day-to-day life of an engineer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While in an academic sense we focus on issues like “training the surrogate costs 100 simulations, but we needed 10,000 simulations for to optimize the building design and thus we saved in the end”, I do not think this calculus is really the major change that surrogates will bring. Even if it takes 100 simulations to train a surrogate that you use 10 times, if you integrate this will cloud compute to do those all in parallel, then to the user you only have to sit through what is effectively 2 simulations. If that’s a two hour simulation time, you’ve now changed a workflow that takes a full day to something that you set to train in the morning and then after lunch you can interactively fiddle with parameters until your controls are correct. And then any time you revisit in the future, it’s ready to be fiddled with again. When you view surrogates in this light, I think you can see why we believe this will be a gamechanger for the everyday engineer.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;one-of-the-main-innovations-brought-by-juliasim-is-the-generation-of-fast-and-accurate-surrogate-models-that-can-speedup-simulations-as-much-as-500x-even-in-the-presence-of-stiff-models-how-is-this-achieved-what-s-a-ctesn&quot;&gt;One of the main innovations brought by JuliaSim is the generation of fast and accurate surrogate models that can speedup simulations as much as 500x, even in the presence of stiff models. How is this achieved? What’s a CTESN?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A continuous-time echo state network (CTESN) is an implicitly trained machine learning framework for capturing the dynamics of stiff models. These are models with phase transitions, fast transient behavior, and are well-known to be numerically difficult. Across many domains we have shown the CTESN training procedure to be robust due to how it incorporates implicit features of stable differential equation solvers. All that we need to generate it is a chunk of simulations done beforehand, and what results is this really fast object that will predict the simulation behavior at new parameters.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-easy-is-it-to-compose-surrogate-models-with-normal-ones-in-juliasim-what-are-the-advantages-of-this-approach&quot;&gt;How easy is it to compose surrogate models with normal ones in JuliaSim? What are the advantages of this approach?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CTESN represents the surrogate of a differential equation model as a differential equation model. Because of this representation, it’s not different from the other physical components. As long as you train it to cover the right states and observables, it will slot right into where you had the larger model before.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;paramount-to-surrogatization-is-the-ability-to-check-the-accuracy-of-the-surrogate-model-and-its-performance-against-the-original-one-how-does-juliasim-tackle-this-are-these-metrics-appropriately-exposed-to-the-user&quot;&gt;Paramount to surrogatization is the ability to check the accuracy of the surrogate model and its performance against the original one. How does JuliaSim tackle this? Are these metrics appropriately exposed to the user?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JuliaSim generates diagnostics of the surrogate training process to signal to the user important features like the projected maximum error over the timeseries over the user-defined parameter space. A lot of this is done through quasi-random sampling right now, though we are investigating more complex techniques to more quickly achieve good estimates.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;does-juliasim-run-on-top-of-juliahub-or-are-they-separate-things-is-the-pricing-model-expected-to-be-the-same&quot;&gt;Does JuliaSim run on top of &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;juliahub.com&#x2F;lp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;JuliaHub&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; or are they separate things? Is the pricing model expected to be the same?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JuliaSim is JuliaHub-based platform. JuliaSim users receive a subscription to a set of proprietary packages, such as the standard library and the surrogatization tools, which grants access to their use on JuliaHub. The pricing model of JuliaSim is simply the subscription and pay-for-compute, so users only pay for what they use but have access to the full suite.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;will-there-be-a-gui-for-modeling-or-will-we-mostly-have-to-write-all-the-julia-code-explicitly&quot;&gt;Will there be a GUI for modeling or will we mostly have to write all the Julia code explicitly?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be many GUIs! The first GUI that we are building is more pharmaceutical modeling focused given our early customer base and connections with Pumas-AI. This allows for quickly building chemical reaction network and systems pharmacology models, and representing models in a visual form for presentations and reporting. It also will serve as the basis for visual programming of compartmental models in pharmacokinetics. We also will have a GUI at launch which simplifies the FMU surrogatization process, allowing non-Julia users to quickly accelerate their FMUs by entering in parameter information and clicking “surrogatize”. We have other GUIs planned for the near future as well, such as GUIs for block diagrams and acausal modeling, along with 3D visualization tools.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;juliasim-is-launching-pretty-soon-what-can-we-expect-from-this-first-version-what-features-are-next&quot;&gt;JuliaSim is launching pretty soon; what can we expect from this first version? What features are next?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JuliaSim’s first beta will be launching fairly soon. I wouldn’t call it the first version quite yet, though the beta will already be usable as we have been working with a group of customers to showcase the performance advantage for their specific applications. The first release will be a mix of GUIs, cloud parallel surrogatization, and standard libraries. And for the future we are aiming for a lot more. The full vision of JuliaSim is expressed in &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=lNbU5jNp67s&quot;&gt;the JuliaCon 2021 video&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; so refer to that for more details.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>BEAM all the things! ClojErl, an implementation of Clojure on the Erlang Virtual Machine</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/clojerl-an-implementation-of-the-clojure-language-that-runs-on-the-beam/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/clojerl-an-implementation-of-the-clojure-language-that-runs-on-the-beam/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/clojerl-an-implementation-of-the-clojure-language-that-runs-on-the-beam/">&lt;h4 id=&quot;an-interview-with-its-creator-juan-facorro&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An interview with its creator, Juan Facorro.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our blog has had a long standing interest in novel uses of the BEAM, or Erlang virtual machine, as shown by the many articles we have published on that topic: we talked to Eric Merritt about &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;eric-merritt-erlang-and-distributed-systems-expert-gives-his-views-on-beam-languages-hindley&#x2F;&quot;&gt;languages that run on BEAM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from a high-level overview, and went deep on &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;an-interview-with-the-creator-of-gleam-an-ml-like-language-for-the-erlang-vm-with-a-compiler&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Gleam&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (an ML-like language for the Erlang VM with a compiler written in Rust), &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;d-day-invasion-with-mlfe-ml-landing-in-the-erlang-world&#x2F;&quot;&gt;MLFE&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (which is short for ML-Flavored Erlang), &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;efene-an-erlang-vm-language-that-embraces-the-python-zen&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Efene&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (an alternative syntax for Erlang), &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;gaming-with-elixir-discovering-new-lands-in-the-beam-realm&#x2F;&quot;&gt;using Elixir for videogame backends&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;lasp-a-little-further-down-the-erlang-rabbithole&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Lasp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (“a suite of libraries aimed at providing a comprehensive programming system for planetary scale Elixir and Erlang applications”).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also published a guide to learn &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;how-to-earn-your-clojure-white-belt&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and an &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;a-pythonist-finds-a-new-home-at-clojure-land&#x2F;&quot;&gt;interview&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that might persuade you to get into it if you haven’t already.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our readers will understand it was inevitable for us to be interested in Juan Facorro’s project, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojerl&#x2F;clojerl&quot;&gt;ClojErl&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. And of course, we interviewed him about it. We hope you enjoy it as much as we did.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;tell-us-a-little-about-clojerl-what-is-it-how-did-it-come-about&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tell us a little about ClojErl, what is it? How did it come about?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ClojErl is an implementation of the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; language that runs on the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;BEAM_(Erlang_virtual_machine)&quot;&gt;BEAM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (the Erlang Virtual Machine).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project started as a learning and exploratory exercise on language implementation. The idea was born out of the combination of my desire to use Clojure at work, and me starting a new job at &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;inaka.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Inaka&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; where I learned to use Erlang (and the BEAM) to build systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that the concurrency model of the BEAM made sense to me, because it provided a framework and some guarantees that made it simple for me to think about concurrency. This has not been the case for me with other concurrency models.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The BEAM was built to solve a practical problem (i.e. high availability communication switches) and solving for concurrency was a big part of the solution, which also included immutable data structures. These two concepts, concurrency and immutability, are also at the core of Clojure’s design principles, so it seemed like a good idea to try to bring this language to the BEAM.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure if I thought about it at the time, but the abstractions on which Clojure is built make using the language a pleasure. The example that I always use is the fact that you can use the &lt;strong&gt;count&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; core function with almost any data structure (it only needs to implement the &lt;strong&gt;ICounted&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; protocol). Even though it is possible to define a function like this in Erlang, I think the resulting code would not be idiomatic Erlang and it would be hard both to maintain and to extend to new types. This is not the case with Clojure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-advantages-does-the-actor-model-bring-over-clojure-s-concurrency-model&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What advantages does the actor model bring over clojure’s concurrency model?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there are absolute advantages of one model over the other.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the way systems are built on the BEAM and the tools it provides (i.e. lightweight processes, monitors and links), it is very suitable for building resilient systems that (when designed right) can recover from failure. This can arguably be done with any language and platform (e.g. Akka on the JVM), but I think it is simpler and easier to do when using the BEAM.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other things are harder and end up being more complex when using Erlang, but I have wondered if this is something that is more related to the size of the community and the problems it is solving, than the language itself. The amount of Elixir libraries that have been written to do almost anything would suggest that this is very likely the case.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;when-would-clojerl-be-a-better-choice-than-regular-jvm-clojure&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When would ClojErl be a better choice than regular JVM clojure?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would say that whenever you need to build a system that is resilient, degrades gracefully and can recover from failures, and you don’t want to spend time on building the mechanism to achieve this from scratch. Using ClojErl will provide a battle-tested platform where all these things are already included in the VM’s design and how systems are built on it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This assumes that you don’t need a very purpose-specific library that exists only in Java, or a Clojure library that is a lot of work to port from Clojure(Script) into ClojErl.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also assumes that there is a library (either in Erlang or maybe other BEAM language) for every one of your needs, which unfortunately is sometimes not the case.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-much-impact-does-losing-java-interop-have-on-the-language-in-everyday-use&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much impact does losing Java interop have on the language in everyday use?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no impact as far as I can tell, although I’m biased :).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything that would necessitate Java interop is either replaced with Erlang interop or an implementation of the set of protocols through which Clojure interacts with the platform (e.g. &lt;strong&gt;IWriter&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;IReader&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for I&#x2F;O).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;there-are-certain-clojure-features-that-are-unsupported-why-is-that&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are certain Clojure features that are unsupported. Why is that?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clojure JVM is implemented on a platform that allows mutability, which is not the case on the BEAM.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;reference&#x2F;transients&quot;&gt;Transient data structures&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for example, rely on the fact that parts of the underlying representation can be updated in-place. The whole point of their existence is to allow for faster operations without the cost of creating new instances after each modification. This cannot be achieved on the BEAM if we want to use the native immutable data structures.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not explored the path of implementing a whole set of data structures through &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;erlang.org&#x2F;doc&#x2F;tutorial&#x2F;nif.html&quot;&gt;NIFs&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that would maybe make this possible. I’m not convinced this is a good idea though, for a number of reasons. The first one is that it would be a lot of work and we would end up with an implementation that needs to be battle-tested before it can be relied upon. The second is that the cost of calling a NIF is not zero and the result might not even provide significant performance gains. And the third is that it would not be possible to use any of the built-in Erlang functions from the standard library or any of the optimizations for them added to the BEAM.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature that is not implemented for Clojure on the BEAM is &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;reference&#x2F;refs&quot;&gt;Refs and Transactions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. This feature is heavily dependent on how the JVM works and it is also not something that is very widely used (as far as I know) in the wild.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ClojErl relies only on the numeric types provided by the platform. This means that things such as ratios, big decimals, and flags about unchecked math are not available. The BEAM is not designed to provide good performance around numerical operations, so if that is your use case you are better off using another set of tools for that purpose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-good-is-the-interoperability-with-erlang-what-about-elixir&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How good is the interoperability with Erlang? What about Elixir?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the design principles for ClojErl was to make interoperability with the platform as seamless as possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A function call to an Erlang function is equivalent to any other Clojure function call: &lt;strong&gt;(module&#x2F;function arg1 arg2 … argN)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data structures are not equivalent, Clojure’s are implemented on top of Erlang’s. All Clojure core functions related to data structures (e.g. count, first, map, etc.) work for all of Erlang’s though, since the necessary protocols are implemented for them to work. It is possible to write expressions for literal Erlang data structures by using the &lt;strong&gt;#erl&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; reader macro before a Clojure literal (e.g. &lt;strong&gt;#erl{:a 1}&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; would be compiled to a literal Erlang map).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before ClojErl currently provides only the numerical data types available on the BEAM: integer (unbound) and float (64 bits).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ClojErl strings are Erlang UTF-8 binaries. It is possible to write literal Erlang strings (i.e. lists of integers) by using the #erl reader macro.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pattern matching is also available in ClojErl when using any of the special forms where bindings are created (i.e. &lt;strong&gt;fn&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;* , &lt;strong&gt;let&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;* , &lt;strong&gt;loop&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;* and &lt;strong&gt;case&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;*).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ClojErl anonymous function can be used as an argument to any of the Erlang BIFs that expect a function, as long as the ClojErl function doesn’t use variadic arity or multiple arities. These two features are specific to Clojure, which means that Erlang code wouldn’t know how to correctly call the function in that case.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story for Elixir is similar to Erlang’s (or any other language on the BEAM). Any function from an Elixir module can be called from ClojErl. Elixir is a little particular in that all its modules have an implicit “&lt;strong&gt;Elixir.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; ” prefix added by the compiler to them. There have been some people recently trying this out with some success (see &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;marcio_lopes&#x2F;status&#x2F;1400256642478903299&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-was-is-the-most-challenging-part-of-the-project&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was&#x2F;is the most challenging part of the project?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most challenging part was and still is finding ways to reconcile what the BEAM offers with the semantics of the Clojure language. Sometimes the conclusion is that we can’t support a feature (e.g. transient collections), other times we need to provide something similar but a little more limited than the original (e.g. vars), and yet other times we add something completely new to the language because we want to have interoperability with platform features (e.g. pattern matching).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another big challenge has been performance. Some features, when implemented on the JVM, do not translate very well to how the BEAM works (e.g. transducers) which results in a much worse performance (i.e. an order of magnitude slower) than what the JVM offers. The release of OTP 24 saw the inclusion of a JIT compiler, preliminary micro-benchmarking using this release showed a lot of improvement in the run time performance of some expressions. There is still quite a lot of work to be done performance wise (both with time and memory usage) on ClojErl.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;are-there-currently-any-interesting-use-cases-for-clojerl&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are there currently any interesting use cases for ClojErl?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we talk about production environment use cases, the short answer is no. The project is still in beta and there hasn’t been (that I know of) any company or individual that has used ClojErl in a production environment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are some use cases that I have found interesting and fun.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of them is &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojerl&#x2F;doodler&quot;&gt;doodler&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is an implementation of a canvas for creating animations inspired in the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;quil.info&#x2F;?example=fireworks&quot;&gt;quil&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; Clojure(Script) project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one is the application behind &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;try.clojerl.online&#x2F;&quot;&gt;try.clojerl.online&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is built in ClojErl. I think I spent more time on the JS client-side console than on the code necessary to have a remote running ClojErl REPL.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;is-the-project-open-for-contributions-if-so-how-should-people-get-started&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is the project open for contributions? If so, how should people get started?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, absolutely, 100%!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are open issues to which I haven’t had time to dedicate myself and anyone that is interested in working on them and any other features or improvements, can reach out through the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojerl&#x2F;clojerl&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;jfacorro&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; ot the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;erlanger.slack.com&#x2F;archives&#x2F;C7KBUEAMC&quot;&gt;#ClojErl Slack channel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fastest way to have a working development environment is by using &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gitpod.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;gitpod.io&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which provides an online IDE for any public project hosted in the major code repositories (e.g. GitHub). Firing up a new environment is as simple as following &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gitpod.io&#x2F;#github.com&#x2F;clojerl&#x2F;clojerl&quot;&gt;this link&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to navigate code is a little bit more complicated because the documentation around this is lacking. There is some documentation in the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clojerl.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;ClojErl.org&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; page and there are also &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;hexdocs.pm&#x2F;clojerl&#x2F;clj_compiler.html&quot;&gt;API docs for the Erlang modules in hex.pm&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. But they provide a limited view and there are some important things that are not included there, therefore until there is more documentation for developing ClojErl I am available for people to reach out with their questions.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other areas that need some love are tools for developing. The &lt;strong&gt;rebar3_ClojErl&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; plugin currently provides pretty good support for compiling, testing, building applications and script; and starting up a REPL. The area that is not so great is the editor support for ClojErl. Syntax highlighting is available and simple to get, but it would be an amazing developer experience if &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;erlang-ls&#x2F;erlang_ls&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erlang-ls&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; could also parse ClojErl files and help navigate the code both in Erlang and ClojErl.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;can-i-use-any-library-written-in-erlang-directly-in-clojerl&quot;&gt;Can I use any library written in Erlang directly in ClojErl?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes! ClojErl is “just” an Erlang library, which means you can combine it with any other Erlang library and&#x2F;or application by using &lt;strong&gt;rebar3&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and the dedicated &lt;strong&gt;rebar3_ClojErl&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; plugin.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>One does not simply build a user interface: our ClojureScript&#x2F;re-frame app</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/one-does-not-simply-build-a-user-interface-our-clojurescript-re-frame-app/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/one-does-not-simply-build-a-user-interface-our-clojurescript-re-frame-app/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/one-does-not-simply-build-a-user-interface-our-clojurescript-re-frame-app/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;notamonadtutorial.com&#x2F;holiday-ping-how-we-implemented-our-first-open-source-app-with-erlang-and-clojurescript-fad5b66fc325&quot;&gt;Part I of this article&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; discussed the motivation to build &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;holidayping.lambdaclass.com&quot;&gt;HolidayPing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and the design and development process of the back end Erlang application. In this follow-up Facundo (the main dev) focuses on the user interface and what we learnt building it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discuss and vote at&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lobste.rs&#x2F;s&#x2F;qlblgh&#x2F;one_does_not_simply_build_user_interface&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;lobsters&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;programming&#x2F;comments&#x2F;7hhrb1&#x2F;one_does_not_simply_build_a_user_interface_our&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;reddit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.ycombinator.com&#x2F;item?id=15844203&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;hn&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;max&#x2F;2000&#x2F;1-BdFV-bGWhQ5HiIL6VfY5xg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before getting into the details, a couple of disclaimers are in order:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Me and most of my coworkers have done front end over the years, but we’re all primarily back end developers. Particularly, the last time I worked on a Single-Page Application, Angular 1 was king; I vaguely knew about React ideas, but never came close to using it.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although we threw in a wizard and a fancy yearly calendar view, the application was your typical CRUD. Exactly the kind of thing for which &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;medium.freecodecamp.org&#x2F;why-i-hate-your-single-page-app-f08bb4ff9134&quot;&gt;you usually don’t want to build a Single-Page application&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. We knew this and we choose to do a SPA anyway because this wasn’t a paid project so we weren’t optimizing for resource efficiency but for learning.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;language-javascript-vs-clojurescript-vs-elm&quot;&gt;Language: JavaScript vs ClojureScript vs Elm&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first big decision was the programming language. JavaScript is the default option, but even with a solid knowledge of the language and coming out of a couple of years with Node.js as my daily work platform, becoming a productive front end JavaScript developer in 2017 is a notable feat. The tooling and even the language keeps moving under your feet. For engineers that only get out of the server from time to time, it all feels like throw-away knowledge (just like my previous Angular experience is of little use today). And if you want to do fashionable JavaScript, you end up using transpilers anyway, so why not just use a different language altogether? I mean, we’re using Erlang already, it’s not like we mind throwing some weirdness into the mix.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elm has always been a very tempting choice for us, but learning an entire language (and one so different from the others I already know) was too much to take on for a side project whose goal was to get familiar with Erlang.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there was ClojureScript. I was already fluent in Clojure, had some experience with ClojureScript, my Emacs was already prepared to move parentheses around… &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=gsffg5xxFQI&quot;&gt;And it delivered its promises&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;lein new re-frame holiday-ping&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is all it took to setup a workflow with a live REPL, hot code reloading (thanks primarily to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;bhauman&#x2F;lein-figwheel&#x2F;&quot;&gt;lein-figwheel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) and advanced JavaScript compilation. This is not only simpler than all the disparate tools you need to do the same job in JavaScript, but also requires a smaller effort than &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;thinkrelevance.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2013&#x2F;06&#x2F;04&#x2F;clojure-workflow-reloaded&quot;&gt;setting up a good workflow in JVM Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;om-vs-reagent-vs-om-next-vs-re-frame&quot;&gt;Om vs Reagent vs Om.next vs re-frame&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was the library or framework to build the UI. We could have gone with a simple DOM manipulation library like &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;plumatic&#x2F;dommy&quot;&gt;dommy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, but we decided — at our own risk — to build a Single-Page App, therefore we looked at React wrappers: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;reagent-project.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Reagent&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;omcljs&#x2F;om&quot;&gt;Om&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. We couldn’t afford to build prototypes with both tools so we have to settle for reviewing the documentation and examples, and getting opinions from friends and the web. As Gandalf once said: &lt;em&gt;all engineers have to do is to pick a library with the time that is given to them&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagent right away seemed more idiomatic Clojure, relying mostly on plain data and functions (and, in the case of re-frame, &lt;em&gt;pure&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; functions) while Om used a lot of objects and protocols, &lt;em&gt;reify&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and JavaScript interop. Reagent also used the lovely hiccup syntax to describe HTML as data, while Om leaned on functions by default (although there are &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;r0man&#x2F;sablono&quot;&gt;libraries to switch to hiccup&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;). Lastly, Om seemed to require a better knowledge of the React lifecycle, which added another layer to get familiar with. A quick comparison of &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;todomvc.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;TodoMVC&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; code illustrates why my gut feeling was to go with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;reagent-project&#x2F;reagent&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;examples&#x2F;todomvc&#x2F;src&#x2F;todomvc&#x2F;core.cljs#L62-L75&quot;&gt;Reagent&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; rather than &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;swannodette&#x2F;todomvc&#x2F;blob&#x2F;gh-pages&#x2F;labs&#x2F;architecture-examples&#x2F;om&#x2F;src&#x2F;todomvc&#x2F;item.cljs#L47-L83&quot;&gt;Om&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I leaned more towards Reagent than Om. But those only provide React wrappers; the real choice had to be between &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;omcljs&#x2F;om&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Quick-Start-%28om.next%29&quot;&gt;Om.next&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;Day8&#x2F;re-frame&quot;&gt;re-frame&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, otherwise I’d had have to come up with an architecture myself, and I didn’t have the background to do it effectively. I caught a great explanation of this by Mike Thompson (author of re-frame) in the Clojurians Slack:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can absolutely use Reagent by itself if your application is simple enough. BUT if you just use Reagent by itself then you only have the V bit of an application. As your application starts to get more complicated, you &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; start to create an architecture which adds &lt;em&gt;control logic&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;state management&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; — the M and C parts (even if you don’t think you are, you are). So then the question becomes: is your architecture better than re-frame’s or not? And some people prefer their own architectures and would answer “yes” :-) Fair enough.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the only danger arises if this process is not conscious — if someone creates a dog’s breakfast of an architecture and doesn’t even know they’ve done it. I’ve had MANY people privately admit that’s what happened to them… and then they swapped to re-frame to get some structure back. So, my advice is… if your application is a little more complicated, be sure to make a conscious choice around architecture, because one way or another you’ll be using one.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;css-framework&quot;&gt;CSS framework&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For styles we went with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;bulma.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Bulma&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: we wanted something lighter than Bootstrap, specifically no JavaScript. Bulma is simple, easy to use, feels lightweight and looks good. In combination with hiccup it meant I was pulling off a beautiful UI without HTML, CSS or JavaScript; all my components were conveniently built by moving Clojure data around Emacs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the one downside was that there aren’t many pre-baked fancy components like Bootstrap has. We kind of made that choice anyway by using ClojureScript in the first place; when we wanted a complex component we either coded it ourselves (we did with tag list inputs) or we avoided them (e.g. no type-ahead selects).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-a-single-page-app-with-clojurescript-and-re-frame&quot;&gt;Developing a Single-Page App with ClojureScript and re-frame&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just needed to read the first few &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;Day8&#x2F;re-frame&#x2F;tree&#x2F;master&#x2F;docs&quot;&gt;re-frame tutorials&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to get started. It felt like re-frame built on the concepts I was already familiar from Clojure and I became reasonably productive in a matter of days, which was amazing considering I hardly knew the first thing about React. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;purelyfunctional.tv&#x2F;guide&#x2F;re-frame-building-blocks&#x2F;&quot;&gt;This guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; provides a good overview of the framework.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, the workflow is amazing: you write pure functions, describing HTML components as Clojure data literals, and figwheel auto reloads them; if you want to play around with a dependency or interop with JavaScript and the browser APIs, just switch to the tab where the REPL is running. Instant gratification all the way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, the re-frame structure can be a little overwhelming: you have events, subscriptions, effects, co-effects… Specially it took me a while to find the justification for subscription handlers, since most of the times they were trivial reads of the database. I think it helped when I read enough times that a design goal of re-frame was to keep views as dumb and decoupled from state as possible; under that light all the pieces started to fall into place: re-frame handles the dirty work and side-effects, you just declare what needs to be done through functions that return data (with the bonus that your code becomes easier to test).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing I don’t quite like about re-frame is how all definitions (reg-event, reg-sub, reg-fx, reg-cofx) set up some hidden application state. I’d prefer to just have standalone functions and pass a map or some other data structure into a single re-frame initialization step. As it is, it forces you to require namespaces just for the side effects they produce, which doesn’t feel very idiomatic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While re-frame is a very opinionated framework and provides a lot structure, there still are some design aspects left to the programmer. Following are some notes of decisions I had to make; a lot of it I figured out along the way and there may be better ways to do it. Critiques and suggestions are certainly welcome.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;routing-and-navigation&quot;&gt;Routing and navigation&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most complex part of the front end application was properly handling navigation. It’s also the place where you pay the penalty of using a SPA framework to build an application that requires browser-like logic (i.e. multiple multiple entry points based on the url, working back&#x2F;forward buttons, etc.).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially it was simple, I just followed the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;Day8&#x2F;re-frame&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;docs&#x2F;Navigation.md&quot;&gt;re-frame documentation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: you add an &lt;em&gt;:active-panel&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; value to your application state, update it when the user produces a navigation event (e.g. select a tab) and make your main view show the proper component based on the &lt;em&gt;:active-panel&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; current value.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #E1E4E8; background-color: #24292E;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;plain&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(def panels {:panel1 [panel1]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;             :panel2 [panel2]})&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defn high-level-view &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  []&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (let [active (re-frame&#x2F;subscribe [:active-panel])]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    (fn []&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      [:div&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;       [:div.title   &amp;quot;Heading&amp;quot;]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;       (get panels @active)])))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was enough to get me going, but my first concern was how to fetch different data from the server based on the selected panel (i.e. when I’m on the channel list, GET &#x2F;api&#x2F;channels; when I’m on the calendar for channel &lt;em&gt;my-channel&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; , GET &#x2F;api&#x2F;channels&#x2F;my-channel&#x2F;holidays; etc.). The first idea that came to mind was to just trigger a request event inside the component view function, but this was directly against the philosophy of keeping logic out of the views.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking in the re-frame Slack channel, I got the suggestion of just fetching all the required data when the user enters the application, load it in the in-memory app-db and use that as the source of truth instead of synchronizing with the server on every step. I wasn’t entirely convinced by this, especially as the application grew bigger, but it was better than polluting view functions with logic and, again, enough to move forward.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, though, the API reached a point where this approach was impractical and inefficient: we had multiple endpoints which more or less mapped to different views in the UI, we couldn’t just load all the data to cover every possible navigation path. Moreover, with very distinct views it was time to bring URLs and the expected browser behavior: proper routing, interacting with the history API. I turned to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;juxt&#x2F;bidi&quot;&gt;bidi&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;kibu-australia&#x2F;pushy&quot;&gt;pushy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, based on a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pupeno.com&#x2F;2015&#x2F;08&#x2F;26&#x2F;no-hashes-bidirectional-routing-in-re-frame-with-bidi-and-pushy&#x2F;&quot;&gt;tutorial by J. Pablo Fernández&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we needed some way to specify what data was to be fetch for each route, without cluttering the views; I came up with a generic event handler, using multimethods:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #E1E4E8; background-color: #24292E;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;plain&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(re-frame&#x2F;reg-event-fx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; :navigate&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; (fn [{:keys [db]} [_ new-view]]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   {;; trigger the load-view event in case data from the server is required&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    :dispatch    [:load-view new-view] &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ;; update the browser history API and switch to the given view&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    :set-history new-view&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ;; set the current view in the app-db so the dom is updated&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    :db          (assoc db&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                        :loading-view? true&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                        :current-view new-view)}))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defmulti load-view&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &amp;quot;Create a multimethod that will implement different event handlers based on the&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   view keyword.&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  (fn [cofx [view]] view))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(re-frame&#x2F;reg-event-fx&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; :load-view&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; (fn [cofx [_ new-view]]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   ;; delegate event handling to the proper multimethod&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   (load-view cofx [vector new-view])))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defmethod load-view &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :default&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  [{:keys [db]} _]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ;; by default don&amp;#39;t load anything&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  {:db (assoc db :loading-view? false)})&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(defmethod load-view&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  :channel-list&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  [_ _]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ;; when navigating to the channel list, fetch the channels&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  {:http-xhrio {:method     :get&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                :uri        &amp;quot;&#x2F;api&#x2F;channels&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                :on-success [:channel-list-success]}})&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though this felt a bit hacky, seeing the view functions become cleaner somewhat validated the approach. For such an opinionated framework, though, I wished there was a recommended way to handle this use case, which is probably a frequent one (maybe there is and I just didn’t find it).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;forms-and-validations&quot;&gt;Forms and validations&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be few tasks as repetitive as writing forms in a web application, specially if there are many CRUD components. After writing a couple of them, I obviously started looking for ways to build a reusable component that would create them based on a specification. I managed to do so, again by resorting to multimethods, such that each method would render differently based on the input type (text, password, select, etc.); the API ended up looking like:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #E1E4E8; background-color: #24292E;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;plain&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;[forms&#x2F;form-view {:submit-text &amp;quot;Register&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                  :on-submit   [:register-submit]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                  :fields      [{:key      :email&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :type     &amp;quot;email&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :validate :valid-email?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :required true}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                {:key      :password&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :type     &amp;quot;password&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :required true}&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                {:key      :password-repeat&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :type     &amp;quot;password&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :label    &amp;quot;Repeat password&amp;quot;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :validate :matching-passwords?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                                 :required true}]}]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The form-view maintains a local state atom, and when the submit button is clicked, the :on-submit event is triggered passing the current input values.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took me a couple of iterations to properly integrate these from components with the rest of the app, specially when I needed to pre-populate them with data coming from other views or from back end responses. This was the one area where I had to get a bit more familiar with React internals, for example learning about &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;goshakkk.name&#x2F;controlled-vs-uncontrolled-inputs-react&#x2F;&quot;&gt;controlled and uncontrolled components&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. After introducing the load-view handler described in the previous section this kind of issues went away.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I needed a way to introduce reusable validations to the form component, without breaking the “no logic in views” rule. I found that encapsulating validation in subscription handlers worked really well. I could specify validations as part of the form specification, subscribe to them to change the style of erroneous inputs and disable submit buttons, and also use the same validations outside of the forms:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;giallo&quot; style=&quot;color: #E1E4E8; background-color: #24292E;&quot;&gt;&lt;code data-lang=&quot;plain&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(re-frame&#x2F;reg-sub&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; :valid-required?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; (fn [db [_ value]]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   (if (string&#x2F;blank? value)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     [false &amp;quot;This field is required.&amp;quot;]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;     [true])))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(re-frame&#x2F;reg-sub&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; :valid-form?&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt; (fn [[_ form fields]]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   (-&amp;gt;&amp;gt; fields&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (get-validation-subs form)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (map re-frame&#x2F;subscribe)&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;        (doall)))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;(fn [validations _]&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;giallo-l&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;   (every? true? (map first validations))))&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a modest project and as such didn’t reveal any higher truth. Instead, it reinforced some ideas and reminded us about things we tend to forget. I liked that it gave us a better perspective than what we’re used to, working mainly as back end engineers: this time we had to write a front end to our APIs and be a user to our interfaces.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good design should model the domain of the problem it is trying to solve, rather than accommodate to immediate client needs. But as engineers we have to expect the user experience to reveal aspects of the domain that we missed, were unforeseeable or plainly didn’t exist at design stage. You need a UI to be able to poke around with the application to see what feels right and what doesn’t, and change the model accordingly. In our case, as soon as we started to use the front end, we realized that the relationships between our entities had to be turned around. What was more interesting: once we made those changes the code became simpler in ways we hadn’t considered.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is no news, but front end takes a lot of work. We were aiming for a very simple UI, one that covered a fraction of the application surface, and it still required more work and way more trial and error than the back end. The dumbest front end application takes a non trivial amount of work to get right and provide an adequate user experience; traditional server-side applications, on the other hand, are becoming easier and easier to put together, to the point that they are arguably becoming extinct.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Holiday Ping: how we implemented our first open source app with Erlang and Clojurescript</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/holiday-ping-how-we-implemented-our-first-open-source-app-with-erlang-and-clojurescript/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/holiday-ping-how-we-implemented-our-first-open-source-app-with-erlang-and-clojurescript/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/holiday-ping-how-we-implemented-our-first-open-source-app-with-erlang-and-clojurescript/">&lt;p&gt;After almost ten years of working as a developer for different companies, two years ago I started my own company &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LambdaClass&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I did so because I wanted to have more freedom in choosing the type of projects and team I work with.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why today it is a very special day for me. We take a break from regular interviews and celebrate the release of our first open source application: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;holidayping.lambdaclass.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Holiday Ping&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Facundo Olano is the main developer of the application. The application was written in two of the best programming languages we know (Clojure and Erlang) and our favorite database (PostgreSQL). This post was written by him and tells his journey and lessons learned with the backend side. A similar post on the frontend will be forthcoming. If you find any issue or want to help check &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;holiday_ping&quot;&gt;github&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discuss and vote at&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lobste.rs&#x2F;s&#x2F;mgefw9&#x2F;holiday_ping_how_we_implemented_our_first&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;lobsters&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;,&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;programming&#x2F;comments&#x2F;7cweat&#x2F;holiday_ping_how_we_implemented_our_first_open&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;reddit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;and&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.ycombinator.com&#x2F;item?id=15695955&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;hn&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;max&#x2F;2000&#x2F;1-9ngymzWNwkPMhZ9u7uZ_XA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year I joined LambdaClass, a Buenos Aires-based software consultant founded a while ago by some colleagues and schoolmates. LambdaClass has a special interest in distributed systems, and while it’s not exclusively an Erlang shop, most of its projects are implemented in &lt;em&gt;BEAM&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; languages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I have a recent background in microservices and functional languages (mainly Clojure), I needed some time to ramp up and gain experience with the OTP platform and its underlying philosophy. I started working on some of the LambdaClass projects right away, but there are aspects of the learning process, specially those related with architecture and design, that are best experienced in greenfield projects. The company also has the goal of a strong open source presence, thus the decision to spend part of my time on public side projects.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We considered a couple of mid sized projects and implemented one of them (which arguably looked smaller in scope than ended up being). The purpose of this document is to share our experience, put some of our discussions into words so we wrap our understanding of them, and make conclusions that can help us in future projects.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-project&quot;&gt;The Project&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;holidayping.lambdaclass.com&quot;&gt;HolidayPing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a small web application that sends holiday reminders through different services like email and slack. It’s mainly aimed at consultants and freelancers used to work with clients abroad. It’s free of charge and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;holiday_ping&quot;&gt;open source&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;spin-off-projects&quot;&gt;Spin-off projects&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the HolidayPing effort, we have started to design and implement some open source tools that solve a couple of problems that we identify as recurring: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;throttle&quot;&gt;throttle&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, to perform access control over resources such as API endpoints, and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;reconnections&quot;&gt;reconnections&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, to initiate and maintain connections to external services in an OTP idiomatic way.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-backend&quot;&gt;The Backend&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;language-erlang-vs-elixir&quot;&gt;Language: Erlang vs. Elixir&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first decision was the programming language: Erlang or Elixir. We use both at LambdaClass, so I’d eventually have to learn them both, the question was which was more effective to learn first, considering both goals of being productive and properly understanding the Erlang platform in the long run.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Elixir would have probably been easier, considering my previous background and that it has a syntax closer to other modern languages. But learning it first carried the risk of just scratching the surface of OTP: using the language like &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=ChUB5Oj2Jj4&quot;&gt;it’s the new Ruby&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and hiding what’s going on underneath. It does seem like it’s simpler to get a good understanding of the “OTP way” by starting with Erlang, especially since &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;learnyousomeerlang.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;there’s literature that guides you through the process&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Then, switching to Elixir would mostly consist of getting familiar with a new syntax and a few language features.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We understand that as Elixir is gaining popularity and more Elixir code is being written, a deeper understanding of Erlang and OTP will become a valuable asset for the company. In addition, many robust and useful libraries are written in Erlang and being able to dive in the code is important.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;learning-erlang&quot;&gt;Learning Erlang&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick note on my impressions of the language: I found it to be very expressive, mostly because of pattern matching; coming from Clojure, I didn’t have issues to grasp Erlang’s functional aspects; contrary to a lot of people, I don’t mind the syntax, I actually like it a lot with the exception of some notable quirks (one comes to mind: binary literals, while very powerful, are very inconvenient as a string replacement). As my coworkers kept telling me and I later confirmed: OTP is the big deal, and not the language itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;application-and-supervisor-structure&quot;&gt;Application and supervisor structure&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a high level, the application can be divided into the following components&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A RESTful API, mostly for CRUD operations.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Process that periodically checks whether reminders should be sent (e.g.: today is a holiday in Bob’s country, and Bob asked to send reminders through slack and email channels).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worker processes that send the reminders.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rest-api&quot;&gt;Rest API&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CRUD API didn’t require much thinking, at least from the OTP point of view. It’s implemented with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;ninenines.eu&#x2F;docs&#x2F;en&#x2F;cowboy&#x2F;2.0&#x2F;guide&#x2F;rest_handlers&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cowboy rest handlers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, and I’ll just note that the library does a great job at forcing you to define a well behaved REST server without too much code.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;reminder-checker&quot;&gt;Reminder checker&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processes involved in the reminders were more interesting, and obviously more important since the value of the application depends on them working properly (&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;jlouisramblings.blogspot.com.ar&#x2F;2010&#x2F;11&#x2F;on-erlang-state-and-crashes.html&quot;&gt;this is the “error kernel” of the app&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process that checks whether holidays should be sent (remind_checker) is a gen_server that uses timer:send_interval to periodically query the database, asking what reminders should be sent. It then triggers worker creation with the necessary data to send the reminders.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How often the checker runs and what information is passed to workers are things that changed as the model and its implementation got more sophisticated, but the general idea was to always isolate the decision to send a reminder from the act of sending it, so a failure in a specific channel wouldn’t affect other channels, other users, or the checker process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;reminder-router&quot;&gt;Reminder router&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reminders are sent by gen_server processes called reminder routers, which are children of a supervisor under a simple_one_for_one strategy. Different channel modules implement the specifics to send the message on each service (email, slack, webhook).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-not-gen-event&quot;&gt;Why not gen_event?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While first studying OTP behaviors, my coworkers suggested I defer reading about gen_event, since it wasn’t used much in practice. When I started to work on HolidayPing, though, which is almost entirely about setting up and triggering events, it sounded like gen_event would be something to consider. And indeed a superficial overview confirmed that; quoting the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.erlang-in-anger.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Erlang in Anger book&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;a gen_event will act as an event hub for callbacks, or as a way to deal with notifications of some sort&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went back to my coworkers: how come we aren’t using gen_event for this? It turns out that this behavior &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.afronski.pl&#x2F;2015&#x2F;11&#x2F;02&#x2F;what-is-wrong-with-gen-event.html&quot;&gt;doesn’t provide much of the benefits&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; one would expect for such an event hub. In terms of what was discussed at the beginning of this section, gen_event does not provide isolation between events, so a slow or crashing event would affect the rest.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-not-worker-pools&quot;&gt;Why not worker pools?&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a certain point in the development, each router was sending the reminders for all the channels of a user on a given holiday. We wanted to further separate processing to have isolated channel requests (e.g. we don’t to bypass email sending if there was a crash requesting Slack).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious option was to add a second simple_one_for_one supervisor with a new gen_server, but we briefly considered a worker pool instead. In other language ecosystems, where threads are expensive, a pool is an usual option. In Erlang, though, the story is different: processes are cheap and there’s no reason upfront to force a limit on the amount of processes being created (with some exceptions, such as maintaining a pool of connections to a database). And if you hit a point where there’s so much work to do that the amount of concurrent processes becomes too expensive, you most likely will need something fancier than a pool to overcome it (i.e. the pool manager will become a bottleneck or the queue will grow faster than workers can process it).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, our situation is atypical in the sense that a potential overload wouldn’t come from requests constantly arriving, but a burst of reminders that need to be sent when the checker runs (currently every 15 minutes). We could easily alleviate this load by spreading the reminders through the time we have between one checker run and the next. Then again, it would be a useless optimization to do this upfront.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;avoiding-throttling-issues&quot;&gt;Avoiding throttling issues&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to an issue that we didn’t notice until I was writing these lines, and that’s &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;holiday_ping&#x2F;issues&#x2F;34&quot;&gt;still open&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. While we don’t have reasons to expect that our system won’t be able to handle sending all reminders at once, it’s likely that the third party services we hit will enforce throttling limits on us.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that hopefully a thousand developers from Argentina find our project useful, and all of them set up a Slack channel, with the default reminder settings. If that’s the case, on Christmas morning at about 9:00am the reminder checker will attempt to send a thousand requests to Slack, more or less at the same time. Slack will likely reject those requests (and their retries next time the checker runs).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to reduce the chance of this happening, would be the same as mentioned in previous section: spread the reminder sending across the available time between one run and the next. Of course, with enough users the limit could be hit anyway and we’d have to resort to finer grained queuing or throttling mechanisms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;database&quot;&gt;Database&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database pick was simple: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;medium.com&#x2F;@jlouis666&#x2F;how-to-build-stable-systems-6fe9dcf32fc4&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;PostgreSQL is the default database&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me it had been years either &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;facundoolano.wordpress.com&#x2F;2012&#x2F;03&#x2F;11&#x2F;django-db-optimization-for-pedestrians&#x2F;&quot;&gt;hiding the database behind an ORM&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, or using schema-less stores like MongoDB. Although the lazy developer inside of me grumbled a bit at having to define the schemas upfront, I eventually came to remember how amazingly flexible and powerful PostgreSQL can be, to the point where I found myself pushing stuff (e.g. time arithmetics) to the database level because it was just easier to work with than the available Erlang libraries. We even &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;holiday_ping&#x2F;issues&#x2F;179&quot;&gt;want to explore&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; domain integrity constraints to implement the long-postponed input validations on the backend.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;handle-the-configuration-differences-between-channels&quot;&gt;Handle the configuration differences between channels&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our model had a spot that was hard to fit in the database schema: the user creates channels that can be of different types (Slack, email, webhook), each with different configuration parameters. The email channel takes a list of email addresses, webhook takes a single url, Slack takes an hook url, a list of channels and users, an emoji, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We care about those differences only in each end of the application: when we validate the user input, and when we execute the type-specific logic to send a reminder; everywhere else, we want to treat the channels equally, regardless of the configuration. We tried several PostgreSQL features to save the channel configuration.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;inheritance&quot;&gt;Inheritance&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This use case seemed like a good fit for &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.postgresql.org&#x2F;docs&#x2F;9.6&#x2F;static&#x2F;ddl-inherit.html&quot;&gt;table inheritance&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;: we wrote a base channel table with all the common fields (user, name, type) and separate tables inheriting from it adding the type-specific configuration. But we soon found out that inheritance features are &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.postgresql.org&#x2F;docs&#x2F;9.6&#x2F;static&#x2F;ddl-inherit.html#DDL-INHERIT-CAVEATS&quot;&gt;very limited&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and don’t provide the features that would justify the choice: unique constraints aren’t enforced across children, you can’t get children’s data when querying the parent, etc.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;plain-tables&quot;&gt;Plain tables&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that inheritance didn’t provide much operational value, using separate tables for configuration and managing them manually made more sense. This is the way to go in the long run, since we want to benefit from type validations and constraints, but compared with a schemaless storage, it would induce a lot of overhead in the early stages of development, considering the channel types and the model in general were far from being stable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;hstore&quot;&gt;hstore&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started looking at unstructured PostgreSQL data types. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.postgresql.org&#x2F;docs&#x2F;current&#x2F;static&#x2F;hstore.html&quot;&gt;hstore&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is a key&#x2F;value type, but it doesn’t have arrays (e.g. more than one value per key). We needed this for channel options, so hstore didn’t do the trick.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;jsonb&quot;&gt;jsonb&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we turned again to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.postgresql.org&#x2F;docs&#x2F;9.5&#x2F;static&#x2F;datatype-json.html&quot;&gt;JSON&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. jsonb fields let us store arbitrary configuration inside the channel table, and treat it like an opaque value except on the spot where we actually use that configuration to send a reminder. Arguably this is the most convenient option only because we never got to the point of thoroughly validating channel input in the backend. When we get there, it will make sense to define properly structured tables first.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rest-api-1&quot;&gt;Rest API&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;identifiers&quot;&gt;Identifiers&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve spent some time discussing ways of identifying our resources across the project. This is a relevant discussion since it applies to most of our projects; we may as well settle with one design and be consistent from now on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we see it, the most flexible method is to use:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A serial ID, just for PostgreSQL. Every table has it, you use it for foreign keys and joins. You don’t want to expose it in the API, since it’s implementation dependent, and something that may not be reusable should you want to switch databases (or add an extra one).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A separate ID to uniquely identify the resource: a UUID that will never change and can be reused across databases.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When it makes sense, a “model” ID for the resource (a user email, an unique name, etc.). You may use it as an identifier in the user facing API (i.e. in the REST uris or the UI routes), to make it user friendly. But you shouldn’t rely on it for internal storage and correlation: even if you start out with an “email won’t change” assumption, business rules like that do change and there’s no benefit in relying too heavily on them for your implementation.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last one is something we didn’t get entirely right, and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;holiday_ping&#x2F;issues&#x2F;113&quot;&gt;there’s still work to do&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Our current implementation has model IDs (user email, channel name, holiday date), but no external UUIDs, so some use cases like changing a channel name are not supported.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;authentication-and-authorization&quot;&gt;Authentication and authorization&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To manage authorization of the API, we went with Bearer tokens based on previous experience. What’s convenient about token authorization, as opposed to, say, requiring Basic Auth on every request, is that it allows us to decouple the authentication from the authorization: if we want to support a new authentication method (which we did when we added GitHub login), we just add a new auth endpoint that returns an access token; authorization on the rest of the API remains untouched.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the token format, I initially went with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;jwt.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;JWT&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; without giving it much thought, because that’s what I’ve seen most commonly used to authorize web apps accessing a REST backend. My coworkers, who haven’t heard about it before, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;lambdaclass&#x2F;holiday_ping&#x2F;issues&#x2F;20&quot;&gt;were suspicious&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, which I understand, because it totally sounds like:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;max&#x2F;2000&#x2F;0-LmkSEubDQc5xYFKb.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we’re &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;medium.com&#x2F;@jlouis666&#x2F;two-technologies-which-are-bad-for-you-160311ad6b24#13fd&quot;&gt;not very fond of JSON&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. So I digged up a little bit more to make sure the decision made sense. There are &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;cryto.net&#x2F;~joepie91&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2016&#x2F;06&#x2F;13&#x2F;stop-using-jwt-for-sessions&#x2F;&quot;&gt;several&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;kev.inburke.com&#x2F;kevin&#x2F;things-to-use-instead-of-jwt&#x2F;&quot;&gt;articles&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; expressing concerns about using JWT, although most of them don’t apply to our use case. Assuming we want to stick to Bearer tokens, the alternative to JWT would be to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;auth0.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;ten-things-you-should-know-about-tokens-and-cookies&#x2F;#token-oauth&quot;&gt;just store a random string in the database&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, associated with the user, and check that value on every request. A quick comparison between the two options:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JWT lets you identify the user without the need to hit the database on every request: the server decodes the token with the same secret it used to generate it, and checks the claims. To be fair, at least in our use case, there’s no evidence that going to the database on each request would be a problem.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JWT is stateless, which seems to be more inline with REST principles: there’s no session, the client sends the token on each request which is enough to identify it.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Database stored tokens require a bit of extra effort: we need to manage expiration ourselves, delete old tokens and make sure we pick a secure enough method to generate them. On the other hand, blacklisting compromised tokens is easier than with JWT, since we can just flag them in the database (although this is &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;stackoverflow.com&#x2F;questions&#x2F;7030694&#x2F;why-do-access-tokens-expire&#x2F;7035926#7035926&quot;&gt;less of an issue&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; using a short expiration).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, JWT is easier (although &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.infoq.com&#x2F;presentations&#x2F;Simple-Made-Easy&quot;&gt;it may not be simpler&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;) than database stored tokens. Either option can work, and I don’t see a strong enough reason to drop JWT having that already working.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;nested-resources&quot;&gt;Nested resources&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the things that we debated but didn’t get to a definite answer. We have these restful resources:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#x2F;api&#x2F;channels&#x2F;:name&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#x2F;api&#x2F;channels&#x2F;:name&#x2F;holidays&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#x2F;api&#x2F;channels&#x2F;:name&#x2F;reminders&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at some point the UI needs to display a summary view that lists channels including their holiday and reminder information.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we do? We obviously don’t want to force the UI to collect the data by making two extra requests per channel in the list. We don’t want to have an API tailor-made for this specific client, either. And don’t say GraphQL, because this is nowhere near big enough to call for that. View saw two acceptable solutions:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a generic query parameter like &lt;code&gt;?children=true&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; to indicate that all the children resources should be included in the response. The problem is that this is an all-or-nothing approach: with big enough resources, you may want some of the children and not all. I’ve seen APIs suffer from that, coming up with weird DSLs to recursively pick nested children in the responses (now, &lt;em&gt;that&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is the case where you’d look at GraphQL nowadays).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider the detailed version of the channel (the one that includes its children information) as a separate resource altogether. At first this too felt a bit like forcing the backend to fit a client need (and, to be honest, looking at the URIs &#x2F;api&#x2F;channels and &#x2F;api&#x2F;channels_detail didn’t help); but after some thinking: better to let resources reproduce and keep the interface as dumb as possible (i.e. no magic query parameters).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could have gone either way. We chose the separate resource because it was easier to implement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;tests&quot;&gt;Tests&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you can’t write serious software without some sort of testing. At some point it’s inefficient to try to make progress without having tests to have your back. But I also think there are situations where being obligated to add tests is counter productive. Apart from the one commandment: &lt;em&gt;thou shalt test thy shit&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; , I don’t like any kind of religiousness about testing. Some types of software benefit a lot from unit tests (testing specific functions, isolated from the rest of the system), some not so much; coverage can be a good indicator, but forcing a specific coverage level sucks; some people work better with TDD, some people work better by adding tests after having some working code; some stuff calls for testing every possible scenario, some for generative testing. Etcetera.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience over the last few years, working on small APIs that mostly deal with connecting to and integrating with external services, there’s little benefit in making pure unit tests. You have to spend a lot of time building mocks to test glue code, and still the most common scenarios can totally fail. If your software deals mostly with integrations, then you need integration tests to have some sort of confidence that your project works and that you don’t break it when you modify it. Because I change it a lot, all the time; that’s something I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; religious about: if you aren’t breaking any APIs, you have the time and you know how to put your code in a better shape, then you do it every time you can.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately my coworkers share the same vision, so for HolidayPing we focused on integration tests that make sure the project works as a whole, with a real database and sending actual reminders. At first with lots of shortcuts to make sure the internal parts were working, but eventually, as development moved forward and the API stabilized, we were able to rewrite the tests so they mostly talk to the external API.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To be continued…&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>A Pythonist finds a new home at Clojure land</title>
          <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/a-pythonist-finds-a-new-home-at-clojure-land/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/a-pythonist-finds-a-new-home-at-clojure-land/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/a-pythonist-finds-a-new-home-at-clojure-land/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome back to another interview of &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;notamonadtutorial.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Not a Monad Tutorial&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. In this opportunity I decided to interview Facundo Olano, a friend, a teammate, and a developer with a &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;facundoolano&quot;&gt;diverse experience&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. We talked about Python, Node.js, Clojure, Common Lisp and software development in general. Something worth mentioning is that this is not the first time Python and Clojure get mentioned together at Not a Monad Tutorial. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;notamonadtutorial.com&#x2F;indie-languages-interview-pixie-and-timothy-baldridge-cadbc36418dc&quot;&gt;Timothy Baldridge implemented Pixie&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a Lisp language inspired by Clojure, in Python.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vote and discuss at &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;lobste.rs&#x2F;s&#x2F;nz28ef&#x2F;pythonist_finds_new_home_at_clojure_land&quot;&gt;lobsters&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;programming&#x2F;comments&#x2F;65ct5j&#x2F;a_pythonist_finds_a_new_home_at_clojure_land&#x2F;&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;news.ycombinator.com&#x2F;item?id=14114624&quot;&gt;hn&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;max&#x2F;2000&#x2F;1-4XmtTGqxc82DyQwcpmr9pw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;A wallpaper I created for my OpenBSD laptop. Lisp, BSD, Erlang, Rust. We live in the best of all possible worlds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are quite in love with Python. Why is that?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heh, love is a big word, isn’t it? But, yes, I guess for a while I had pretty strong feelings for Python. I still have, to a degree. If you’re going with the love metaphor let’s say I had a series of shitty girlfriends that didn’t treat me all that well and I didn’t even noticed it, then I meet this great woman, this caring and interesting woman that listens to what I have to say and doesn’t, um, force me to wrap everything in class.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously speaking, I learnt to program in college, arguably at an old age, and there they taught me Pascal (because some folks are convinced that’s still the best way to teach good programming manners), then a fair amount of C++, and lots of Java. Everybody was in love with Java over there and they kind of gave you the impression that that was it: this is as good as programming gets, this is what will get you a job and it’s so much better than C++, which I already knew wasn’t pleasant to work with. So I got a job programming Java and I loved it, I read all the books, &lt;em&gt;Refactoring&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and the Design Patterns stuff. But then I had to quit because I was getting behind in College, I got some free time back and I was curious about Python because some former coworkers and other students talked heavens about it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got this book &lt;em&gt;Learning Python&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and went through it top to bottom one summer. I guess I felt scammed, in a way: how come nobody told me about this? I felt I had been wasting my time writing XMLs and type hierarchies, while there was a simpler way to do about everything: dynamic typing gave me polymorphism for free, the data structures were built-in and had literals, string manipulation was just amazingly easy, you could have standalone functions and pass them like values, a lot of the Java design patterns were reduced to one-liners… I guess one of the take-aways of the experience was that sometimes your peers know better than your teachers (or your bosses).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But besides it feeling better than Java, what’s still unique for me about Python is the set of principles that are best expressed in the &lt;em&gt;Zen of Python&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. It felt like every bit of the language followed those principles and it encouraged you to do the same with your own code; when in doubt about how to tackle something, the Zen of Python would tell you the right way to go. I still follow most of those ideas when I program, regardless of the language.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before learning Clojure, your&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;facundoolano.wordpress.com&#x2F;2012&#x2F;01&#x2F;31&#x2F;first-impressions-on-common-lisp&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;first experience with a Lisp&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;was with Common Lisp. From what I have talked with you about learning Common Lisp I could sum up that it was a bittersweet experience. Why didn’t you like Common Lisp?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got interested in Lisp after reading Paul Graham essays. Then there was that bit of Eric Raymond about the religious experience of &lt;em&gt;getting&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Lisp. After what I went through with Java and Python I made a point about always looking for chances to learn new languages.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it just didn’t feel right, in a lot of ways it was the opposite of what I loved about Python: the code was very difficult to read (not because parens or prefix notation, just because it was filled with symbols), the operator set was huge, with really weird names and not dynamic at all, I remember it having like six equality operators for different types. Add to that it’s an old language with a small community and zero chances of getting a job using it, it made no sense to invest much time in it, since it wasn’t fun either. But fortunately there are many Lisps and I already knew right then I’d give a chance to Clojure eventually.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why was the experience with&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;facundoolano.wordpress.com&#x2F;2016&#x2F;03&#x2F;20&#x2F;first-impressions-on-clojure&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clojure different&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;? As&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;programming&#x2F;comments&#x2F;65ct5j&#x2F;a_pythonist_finds_a_new_home_at_clojure_land&#x2F;dg97mao&#x2F;&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stesch said in reddit&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, Clojure land is in the Java sea. Those are strange waters for a pythonist. What did you like about it?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, it addresses everything that put me off about Common Lisp. It’s more readable. The operator set is big, but very consistent and polymorphic: all core functions work as expected with every data type. It has a strong focus on immutability and functional programming, which CL hadn’t. But it’s also a very pragmatic language: it doesn’t ask you to learn category theory or to know what a functor is in order to get why you would benefit from it. That’s the approach to functional programming that I like. I’m not saying theory isn’t important, just that I’m the kind of programmer whose interest you won’t catch with theory detached from practice. Also, the community is very active and welcoming, and the fact that it’s a JVM language makes it get a lot of attention, considering it’s a Lisp dialect.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that made me feel at home about Clojure is that it has a strong philosophy and you can tell its design has been driven by it. The philosophy is not the same as the one in Python, and now I understand that that doesn’t really matter. I want consistently opinionated languages rather than bags of features you can bend to program in ten different ways; &lt;em&gt;what&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; the philosophy is is secondary to the fact that &lt;em&gt;there is&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a philosophy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks by Rich Hickey are enlightening, and every time I watch one I feel like I improved my understanding of the language, even if the talk isn’t about Clojure itself. Kind of like a Zen of Clojure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think about the JVM and its community?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working to suppress the strong feelings I used to have against Java. I still dislike it as a language and the way of programming it encourages, though. I revisited it a couple of years ago to write some Android apps and nope, still not my cup of tea. Everything just feels convoluted and over engineered, I’d constantly think how much simpler this is in Python or Perl or Ruby or JavaScript. It’s a very programmer-centric view, I’m aware, mostly based in what I enjoy in the day to day, which doesn’t necessarily make sense from a business perspective. There’s a reason why big companies go to Java; I recognize there’s a lot of top of the class software written in it, and it’s fast. I don’t have the background to make a serious assessment of the JVM but I’m pretty sure it’s an amazing piece of software.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good thing is the JVM can now host other languages, and something as weird as a functional Lisp dialect is fairly close to being popular and you can even get a job with it. That’s a lot to say.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you miss from Python?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I say, half-joking, that programming is a branch of literature. In that sense I value elegance and succinctness, I think there can be beauty in code, but I also know that beauty is completely subjective and I can’t argue about one style being better than another. I’m not talking about readability, that’s important and it’s more or less measureable; I’m talking about aesthetics. I think Python had that kind of beauty for me, which is harder to get in Clojure. Clojure can be more expressive and it’s more powerful but can easily get ugly if you don’t have a lot of discipline. Again: all subjective stuff.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truth be told, I don’t think I miss Python all that much, at least not while I’m doing Clojure. JavaScript is a different story, JavaScript is a mess. But still, if you bend it in the right directions, it can be a fairly decent functional language. I noticed that Python can’t, there’s stuff that just doesn’t work that way (lambdas come to mind), and that probably would annoy me nowadays. So I guess I’m not married to any language anymore. That’s a good thing, right?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your most known projects in Github are written in JavaScript. Do you like coding in JavaScript?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JavaScript is Frankenstein. As Douglas Crockford showed in &lt;em&gt;The Good Parts&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; years ago, there’s a lot of awful bits and you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; to subset the language. That’s gotten worse, because they keep adding stuff to it (some of it really cool, some of it to make it look like Java), and they can’t remove the old stuff, so it has become one of those things you have to agree upfront on which parts you’re going to use and which parts are banned, kind of like C++.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as said, if you pick the right subset it can be good. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;eslint.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;eslint&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; helps. If you ban &lt;em&gt;this&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;new&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and treat objects like maps, most problems go away. If you’re bold you can even pick a set of eslint rules to force immutability. And then there’s &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;ramdajs.com&quot;&gt;Ramda&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. That’s the secret sauce; it makes data manipulation a joy, in some spots I even like its functions better than their Clojure counterparts. The async stuff is weird. I still can’t make my mind if Promises are better than callbacks, but I got used to them. It’s a lousy way of hiding concurrency, though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a fair amount of Node.js projects in GitHub, yes. That’s the killer thing about Node.js: NPM, its ecosystem, this philosophy of small unix-y modules. You have an idea, you write up a file and you’re two commands away from publishing it and getting feedback. No other language I’ve tried reduces the boilerplate to share your work that much. That’s a real boost for Open Source and Collaboration. I recognize it has some bad side effects (mixed module quality, left-pad, etc.), but those are much less than the advantages. I remember Python dependency and publishing story being way more cumbersome.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the last few months you started using Emacs. What do you think about it?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been putting off a blog post about that. I know I’m glad that I decided not to learn Emacs at the same time that I was learning Clojure. That could have caused me to drop both things. I think there’s this idea that you can’t learn a Lisp without Emacs, and that may have been true before, but now that there’s &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;shaunlebron.github.io&#x2F;parinfer&#x2F;&quot;&gt;parinfer&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; you can safely hack Lisp on most modern editors. Hardcore lispers may not notice how amazing of a contribution to the community this is, it makes it dramatically easier to get started with Lisp and reachable to people that wouldn’t even consider using something like Emacs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pleasantly used Clojure with Sublime and parinfer for almost a year. Then I started reading &lt;em&gt;Coders at work&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; and saw all these amazing hackers mentioning Emacs again and again. It felt like I was missing out on something, so I decided I should give it a try, as a weekend project.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was a hell of weekend. The first lesson I learned was that I was a shitty typist, but that got better as the days went by. Fortunately it was a quiet week at work because I could barely get anything done for a while. One interesting note is that I went through this process with JavaScript, so I could make Emacs my daily editor at work. It wasn’t until I felt comfortable with the editor that I tried it with Clojure. And then I realised my Clojure experience wasn’t complete before. It probably goes the other way around: you get the best out of Emacs when you’re doing Lisp.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I’d recommend it to every programmer, though, specially if they work on a single language that already has a killer editor. Learning Emacs is a really fun and enriching experience, but you have to be prepared to spend a lot of time tuning the editor at first and acknowledge the fact that &lt;em&gt;your Emacs config will be the project of your life&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; , as I read somewhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I love those times when you realise you are doing something repeatedly, that could be done by a command, and you write it (or, better, you find that someone else wrote it already). That’s when it pays off.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there any particular Clojure library that you would specially recommend?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jonase&#x2F;kibit&quot;&gt;kibit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; I find amazing because it’s not only a useful linter (like &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jonase&#x2F;eastwood&#x2F;&quot;&gt;eastwood&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; also is), but it teaches you the standard library as you go, which can be a little bit overwhelming when you are starting out. &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;bhauman&#x2F;lein-figwheel&quot;&gt;Figwheel&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is another obvious one that made a big difference for me when I started to play with ClojureScript.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;macchiato-framework.github.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Macchiato framework&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is doing a great job of bringing Node.js to ClojureScript.**** I noticed some people don’t take Node.js very seriously, but being Clojure a language that makes such a strong point of leveraging the host platform, the world of possibilities available in NPM can’t be disregarded. There’s another often overlooked fact: you’re much more likely to find a functional programming enthusiast nowadays doing Node.js than in the Java world, so shortening that gap can only bring good to the community.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;candid82&#x2F;joker&quot;&gt;Joker&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is another great one. It’s a Clojure interpreter written in Go, but what I’ve found incredibly useful is how it works as a linter, which you can easily hook to an editor. It really improved my workflow, early catching typos and bugs while I program.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the testing related work I’ve been doing recently I’ve found &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jakemcc&#x2F;lein-test-refresh&quot;&gt;lein-test-refresh&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;weavejester&#x2F;eftest&quot;&gt;eftest&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to be useful and insightful about how clojure.test and leiningen internals work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On your github profile you have many pretty well known open source projects. What motivates you to invest time in them?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just love programming. I have lots of hobbies, but definitely programming is one of the things that I enjoy the most, what gives me the most pleasure. It’s like an itch: I get this idea or I encounter a need that isn’t addressed by an existing library or maybe I’m just playing to learn a new technology. I can’t help it but sitting down and building something, until is see something working on the screen and the itch goes away. I learned not to be lazy, polishing it a bit and uploading it to GitHub.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is ideal, because you get to work on your own time, you do the stuff you’re interested in and drop the project whenever it bores you. I wish someone would pay me to do that. With a real job it’s harder: sometimes it gets boring, sometimes there’s nothing to do or you depend on someone else to move forward. Most often than not you can’t share your work.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I always liked this process of conceiving a project, executing it and sharing it with others. Not just in software; the same goes for my fiction writing or when I recorded music as a teenager. When I was in high school I didn’t know how to program but I was obsessed with making games, I spent most of my afternoons fiddling with these game maker programs, RPG Maker and such, sharing my creations with friends. Unfortunately internet access was limited at home and they didn’t teach programming in my school, so it wasn’t until much later that I was able to do serious stuff on my own.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During college I did little projects and games but the languages I knew and skills I had weren’t enough to get me very far at the beginning. There was no GitHub, so it was harder to share and find interesting projects to work on. Later I had to juggle between a full-time job and finishing college. It wasn’t until these last couple of years that I got the freedom to work on whatever I want. And I know in a couple of years I’ll have kids and other stuff going on in my life, so I’m trying to enjoy this programming spring as much as I can.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then there’s marketing factor. I’m not great at some types of job interviews and my resume may not tell you that much on its own, but I have a portfolio of open source projects that shows I’m a serious coder, a published Android game that proves I can take a personal project to production and a blog that tells you that I reason about my craft and I’m constantly trying to improve it. If you care enough to read it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are you working on lately?&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I work on a Node.js shop, but the team is full of functional enthusiasts. We can’t convince our boss to let us write a production microservice in Clojure or Elixir, or a user interface in Elm. But the boss doesn’t care that much about our integration tests (as long as there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; tests). So when someone complained for the zillionth time about how painful it is to write our API integration tests in JavaScript, I proposed migrating them to Clojure. To my surprise they agreed. So I hacked together this little library to easily do all that we were already doing in our Node.js API tests. And I liked how it turned out, so I’ve &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;facundoolano&#x2F;restpect&quot;&gt;published it in GitHub&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Nothing too fancy but it was a good excuse to escape from JavaScript, and it got three of my coworkers learning Clojure, which is great news.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I keep slowly growing my &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;facundoolano&#x2F;advenjure&quot;&gt;advenjure engine&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;; just &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;facundoolano.github.io&#x2F;house-taken&quot;&gt;published a full game&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with it, based on a story by Julio Cortázar. Also been doing some &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cljsbin-bkhgroqzwe.now.sh&#x2F;&quot;&gt;experiments with Macchiato&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, to write Clojure web apps that run on Node.js. I have this Machine Learning book I’m about to start, see where that takes me. Node.js microservices still pay my bills. For now, I guess. At some point I hope to be able to get paid for writing Clojure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>How to earn your Clojure white belt</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/how-to-earn-your-clojure-white-belt/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/how-to-earn-your-clojure-white-belt/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.lambdaclass.com/posts/how-to-earn-your-clojure-white-belt/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;&#x2F;images&#x2F;max&#x2F;2000&#x2F;1-uFlthCHz1YbmOvzhdVBrFw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to think that if I do not know how to implement something then I do not undestand completely how it works. That is why I want to learn so many things: new frameworks, programming languages, garbage collectors, type systems, compilers, editors, operating systems, protocols, kernel development. The road to enlightenment is long and difficult. To make things worse, you need to invest time on keeping up to date with technologies you thought you already knew. I usually feel like Mario in one of those levels where he needs to jump between moving clouds to reach the finish line.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why one of the best skills to get is being able to separate the wheat from the chaff. We have finite time and distractions are infinite. If you are going to invest time in learning a new language then you should consider Lisp which is definitely wheat of the best quality. If you don’t know why, then go read &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.paulgraham.com&#x2F;avg.html&quot;&gt;Beating the Averages&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; article. Clojure is a member of the Lisp family. If you have used a Lisp dialect such as &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.schemers.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Scheme&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;common-lisp.net&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Common Lisp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Emacs_Lisp&quot;&gt;Emacs Lisp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, or even really alien and amazing creatures such &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.shenlanguage.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Shen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lfe.io&#x2F;&quot;&gt;LFE&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;racket-lang.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Racket&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;pixie-lang&#x2F;pixie&quot;&gt;Pixie&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; you might ask yourself why you should be learning Clojure. This is my opinionated point of view:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The language’s creator: Rich Hickey has a holistic understanding of this era development issues. You should read&#x2F;watch his talks called &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;matthiasn&#x2F;talk-transcripts&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;Hickey_Rich&#x2F;AreWeThereYet.md&quot;&gt;Are We There Yet?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;matthiasn&#x2F;talk-transcripts&#x2F;blob&#x2F;master&#x2F;Hickey_Rich&#x2F;SimpleMadeEasy.md&quot;&gt;Simple Made Easy&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;ROor6_NGIWU&quot;&gt;The Language of the System&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. I see Clojure as a step in the right direction for tackling this era’s development issues&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great functional programming support: First class functions, persistent, immutable data structures and lazy &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.braveclojure.com&#x2F;core-functions-in-depth&#x2F;#2__The_Sequence_Abstraction&quot;&gt;sequences&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. It has great support of polimorphism thanks to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure-doc.org&#x2F;articles&#x2F;language&#x2F;polymorphism.html&quot;&gt;multimethods and protocols&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurrency support from its inception thanks to &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure-doc.org&#x2F;articles&#x2F;language&#x2F;concurrency_and_parallelism.html&quot;&gt;atoms, agents, refs, a software transactional memory &lt;&#x2F;a&gt;system and asynchronous programming using channels a la &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Communicating_sequential_processes&quot;&gt;CSP&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;2013&#x2F;06&#x2F;28&#x2F;clojure-core-async-channels.html&quot;&gt;core.async&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; library&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Batteries included: good core libraries and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=6mTbuzafcII&quot;&gt;transducers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; support&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clojurescript: Clojure that targets JavaScript with great libraries such as &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;reagent-project&#x2F;reagent&quot;&gt;reagent&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, an interface to React.js that is really simple and useful. Check David Nolen’s talks called ClojureScript: &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;MTawgp3SKy8&quot;&gt;Lisp’s Revenge&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;youtu.be&#x2F;-I5ldi2aJTI&quot;&gt;Introduction to ClojureScript&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JVM’s power (available almost everyhwere, optimized garbage collector, JIT compilation, Java interoperability), but also some issues such as not being able to properly support tail call optimization and awful stacktraces. If you are a Java developer you should check part &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=P76Vbsk_3J0&quot;&gt;I&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;watch?v=hb3rurFxrZ8&quot;&gt;II&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from Rich Hickey’s Clojure for Java Programmers talk&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ready-steady-go&quot;&gt;Ready, steady, go!&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;leiningen.org&#x2F;#install&quot;&gt;Leiningen&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and configure your editor of choice.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emacs with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojure-emacs&#x2F;cider&quot;&gt;Cider&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojure-emacs&#x2F;clojure-mode&quot;&gt;Clojure mode&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;company-mode.github.io&quot;&gt;Company mode&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vim with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;tpope&#x2F;vim-fireplace&quot;&gt;vim-fireplace&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;tpope&#x2F;vim-sexp-mappings-for-regular-people&quot;&gt;im-sexp-mappings-for-regular-people&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;tpope&#x2F;vim-salve&quot;&gt;vim-salve&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;luochen1990&#x2F;rainbow&quot;&gt;rainbow&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;lighttable.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Light Table&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;sekao.net&#x2F;nightcode&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Nightcode&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sublime with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;odyssomay&#x2F;paredit&quot;&gt;paredit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;odyssomay&#x2F;sublime-lispindent&quot;&gt;Lispindent&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.google.com.ar&#x2F;search?q=SublimeREPL&quot;&gt;SublimeREPL&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cursiveclojure.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Cursive&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (IntelliJ)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;doc.ccw-ide.org&#x2F;documentation.html#install-as-standalone-product&quot;&gt;Counterclockwise&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (Eclipse)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;good-tools-that-deserve-a-mention&quot;&gt;Good tools that deserve a mention&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linter &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jonase&#x2F;eastwood&quot;&gt;Eastwood&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Idiomatic Clojure checker &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jonase&#x2F;kibit&quot;&gt;kibit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clojure formatter &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;weavejester&#x2F;cljfmt&quot;&gt;cljfmt&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check simple issues in your code &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;dakrone&#x2F;lein-bikeshed&quot;&gt;bikeshed&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;love-at-first-sight&quot;&gt;Love at first sight&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all get an idea of Clojure syntax and semantics:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;learnxinyminutes.com&#x2F;docs&#x2F;clojure&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Learn X in Y minutes where X=clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;kimh.github.io&#x2F;clojure-by-example&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure by example&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;howistart.org&#x2F;posts&#x2F;clojure&#x2F;1&#x2F;&quot;&gt;How I start Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.se-radio.net&#x2F;2010&#x2F;03&#x2F;episode-158-rich-hickey-on-clojure&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Listen to Software Engineering Radio’s interview with Rich Hickey&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not understand something move on. At this stage the only objective is to grasp some basic ideas about Clojure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;practice-plus-reading-equals-perfection&quot;&gt;Practice plus reading equals perfection&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First practice with the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojurekoans.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Koans&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then read &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.braveclojure.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure for the Brave and True&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, a simple and short book. If you prefer to watch videos, you can buy the course &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.purelyfunctional.tv&#x2F;intro-to-clojure&quot;&gt;Introduction to Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; from PurelyFunctionalTV.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice again with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.4clojure.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;4clojure problems&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the road to perfection with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;exercism.io&#x2F;languages&#x2F;clojure&quot;&gt;Clojure exercism&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finish the practice with &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;gigasquid&#x2F;wonderland-clojure-katas&quot;&gt;Wanderland Clojure Katas&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always a good idea to have the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojure.org&#x2F;api&#x2F;cheatsheet&quot;&gt;cheatsheet&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at hand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other two good tutorials worth mentioning are &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;aphyr.com&#x2F;tags&#x2F;Clojure-from-the-ground-up&quot;&gt;Clojure from the ground up&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;hitchhikersclojure.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Hitchhiker’s Guide to Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;idiomatic-clojure&quot;&gt;Idiomatic Clojure&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clojure is not Java, neither Common Lisp or Scheme. You should learn to write idiomatic Clojure. The Joy of Clojure is your best friend to become a native Clojure speaker:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.joyofclojure.com&#x2F;the-book&#x2F;&quot;&gt;About The Joy of ClojureWhen this book was conceived, our first instinct was to create a comprehensive com- parison between Clojure and its…www.joyofclojure.com&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;cdn-images-1.medium.com&#x2F;fit&#x2F;c&#x2F;160&#x2F;160&#x2F;0*B4upiW5LhjZYt_TK.&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also important to follow table manners or the &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;bbatsov&#x2F;clojure-style-guide&quot;&gt;Clojure style guide&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have trouble like me grasping macros, then you should also check out &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pragprog.com&#x2F;book&#x2F;cjclojure&#x2F;mastering-clojure-macros&quot;&gt;Mastering Clojure Macros&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, if you miss your type checking then now it is a good time that you read about &lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;typedclojure.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;optional type system&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for Clojure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;keep-up-to-date&quot;&gt;Keep up to date&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;planet.clojure.in&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Planet Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clojuregazette.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure Gazette&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;reborg.tumblr.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure Weekly&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.reddit.com&#x2F;r&#x2F;Clojure&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;user&#x2F;ClojureTV&quot;&gt;ClojureTV&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;know-the-full-arsenal-at-your-disposal&quot;&gt;Know the full arsenal at your disposal&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.clojure-toolbox.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojure Toolbox&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;razum2um&#x2F;awesome-clojure&quot;&gt;Awesome Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;get-help&quot;&gt;Get help&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;groups.google.com&#x2F;forum&#x2F;#!forum&#x2F;clojure&quot;&gt;Google Group&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IRC: #clojure channel in Freenode server&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;clojurians.slack.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Clojurians Slack&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;introduction-to-clojurescript&quot;&gt;Introduction to Clojurescript&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clojure on the frontend trench:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojure&#x2F;clojurescript&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Quick-Start&quot;&gt;Quickstart&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;clojure&#x2F;clojurescript&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Differences-from-Clojure&quot;&gt;Differences from Clojure&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;magomimmo&#x2F;modern-cljs&quot;&gt;A series of tutorials on Clojurescript&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;building-your-own-lisp&quot;&gt;Building your own Lisp&lt;&#x2F;h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building a Lisp is similar to a road trip with friends and good music but with no particular destination. Make yourself comfortable and enjoy the ride!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.buildyourownlisp.com&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Build your own Lisp&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikibooks.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Write_Yourself_a_Scheme_in_48_Hours&quot;&gt;Write Yourself a Scheme in 48 hours&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a rel=&quot;noopener external&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;norvig.com&#x2F;lispy.html&quot;&gt;(How to Write a (Lisp) Interpreter (in Python))&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
